Guide to the Ardath W. Burks Papers, 1928-1996
Special Collections and University Archives, Rutgers University Libraries
Guide to the Ardath W. Burks Papers
1928-1996
Burks, Ardath W.
15.5 cubic ft. (39 legal size manuscript boxes, 7 letter size manuscript boxes, 1 photograph box, 4 oversize boxes)
Rutgers University Libraries. Special Collections and University Archives.
The Ardath W. Burks Papers, 1928-1996, are those maintained and created by Ardath W. Burks, Rutgers University administrator and Professor of Asian Studies. The papers contain material relating to both Burks' personal and public activities. Personal activities relate to his family and home life. His relationship with Japan, manifested in many ways, dominates his public activities; Burks' education, military service, promotion of positive relationships between Japan and the United States, and his academic career and endeavors relating to academia comprise elements of his public activities. However, the line of demarcation between the two spheres of activity blurs often, and documents like correspondence frequently contain information related to a myriad of topics, such as his family life, academic activities, and participation in Sister Cities International programs.
R-MC 083
Biographical Sketch
Ardath Walter Burks was born May 1, 1915 in Covington, Kentucky to Alonzo Edwin Burks, an assistant freight agent for the C O Railroad, and Clara Grace McCracken Burks. He married Virginia Jane Lyle Burks on November 15, 1941; their son, Stephen Riki Burks, was born in 1954.
Burks received his B. A. from the University of Cincinnati in 1939, his M. A. from the University of Minnesota in 1941, and his Ph.D. from the School of Advanced International Studies at Johns Hopkins University in 1949. However, World War II interrupted his progress towards his doctorate. He served as an Associate Economic Analyst for the Office of Naval Intelligence from 1941 to 1943. In 1943, upon obtaining a release from his deferment, Burks enlisted in the United States Navy. He pursued intensive language training through the Naval Training School (Oriental Languages) at the University of Colorado, Boulder, where he received his certification in Japanese on April 15, 1944, and then attended the Advanced Naval Intelligence School in New York City. Afterwards, he was commissioned as a lieutenant (junior grade) in the U. S. Naval Reserves, and served as a Language Officer throughout the remainder of the war. He was released from active duty in 1946, although he continued to serve as a civilian Air Intelligence Specialist until September.
Burks' career at Rutgers, the State University of New Jersey commenced in 1948 when he joined the faculty as a professor of Political Science. He remained in this department, serving as its chairman from 1962 through 1965. In 1966 he accepted a position as a Visiting Professor for the East Asian Institute at Columbia University. He returned to Rutgers in the fall of 1966, moving into administrative duties as the Director of International Programs until 1973. In 1973 Burks joined the formal administration of Rutgers as the Associate Vice President for Academic Affairs. His efforts to establish a Department of Asian Studies culminated in his appointment as the first Professor of Asian Studies in 1977. He formally retired in 1981, and was subsequently recognized as a Professor Emeritus of Asian Studies.
During his academic career, Burks remained active in research and writing and made numerous research trips. Amongst other positions, he was a Research Associate and the Acting Field Director for the University of Michigan Center for Japanese Studies in Okayama (1952-1953); a Senior Research Fulbright Fellow for Humanistic Studies at Kyoto University (1958-1959); a recipient of the Ford Travel-Study Grant, representing Rutgers and acting as a liaison with Tokyo Metropolitan University (1962); a Resident Consultant of the International House of Japan, Inc., in Tokyo (1965); and a consultant for the Council on International Educational Exchange (1970, 1973).
Burks supported many endeavors related to Japanese studies, such as the Japan Society in New York and the International House of Japan in Tokyo. He was also heavily involved in the Association for Asian Studies, serving on its Board of Directors (1972-1975) and as the Chairman for the Northeast Asia Regional Council (1972-1973). He participated in the prestigious Columbia University Seminar on Modern East Asia: Japan, from its inception in 1963, serving as its chairman on two occasions: 1966-1967 and 1987-1988. From 1956 to 1964, Burks was the director of various summer institutes for secondary school teachers dedicated to raising interest in Asian Studies in pre-college students. The first of these institutes was held at the University of Delaware in 1956; later ones took place at Temple University, the University of Hawaii, and Rutgers University.
From the beginning of his tenure at Rutgers, Burks devoted his energies to reviving interest in Japan and renewing ties between Rutgers and Fukui University which had originated in the mid-nineteenth century. With his enthusiastic promotion and participation, Rutgers University and Fukui University built a collaborative relationship manifested in various activities such as: the formation of Rutgers-kai, the Rutgers Association of Fukui (1978); the establishment of the Griffis-Kusakabe Fund (1978); and the creation of a formal exchange program between Rutgers and Fukui University (1981). Burks also actively supported positive relations between the United States and Japan on local and national levels. Due in part to his enthusiasm, New Brunswick signed a Sister Cities agreement with the city of Fukui in 1982, and New Jersey entered into a sister state agreement with Fukui Prefecture in 1990. In 1982, Burks was recognized as an honorary citizen of Fukui.
Burks was in many ways responsible for promoting the William Elliot Griffis Collection, held by Special Collections and University Archives, Rutgers University Libraries. The Griffis Collection documents the life of Griffis, who was one of the first oyatoi gaikokujin (foreign employees) serving in the Meiji government. Griffis was also involved in tutoring a number of ryûgakusei (overseas students) who studied at Rutgers in the mid to late nineteenth century. Burks' later research centered on the yatoi and ryûgakusei. He helped organize two major conferences on the yatoi, one at Rutgers in 1967 and one at Fukui University in 1985, which were attended by distinguished Asian Studies scholars from around the world. The proceedings of the 1967 conference were published as The Modernizers: Overseas Students, Foreign Employees, and Meiji Japan (Kindaika no suishintach; ryugakusei, oyatoi-gaikokujin to Meiji), and those of the 1985 conference as Foreign Employees in Nineteenth Century Japan (Za Yatoi).
After retirement, Burks maintained his ties to Rutgers University and Fukui. He helped found Rutgers University Academy for Lifelong Learning (RU-ALL). He acted as a volunteer member of the Sister-Cities Committee of New Brunswick, and advised New Brunswick Mayor John Lynch as a member of a delegation from New Brunswick to Tokyo, Tsuruoka, Fukui, and Kyoto. Other volunteer positions held by Burks included being a consultant for Rutgers University Special Collections and University Archives and a counselor for the Zimmerli Art Museum and International Center for Japonisme at Rutgers University. The Japanese government decorated him in 1990 with the Order of the Rising Sun, Gold Rays with Neck Ribbon.
Jane Lyle Burks died in 1991. Ardath Burks currently resides in Basking Ridge, New Jersey.
Scope and Content Note
The Ardath W. Burks Papers date from 1928 to 1996, with the bulk of the material dating from between 1970 and 1990. The papers are approximately 15.5 cubic feet in size; they include thirty-nine legal size manuscript boxes, seven letter size manuscript boxes, one photograph box, and four oversize boxes.
The papers contain material relating to both Burks' personal and public activities. Personal activities relate to his family and home life. His relationship with Japan, manifested in many ways, dominates his public activities; Burks' education, military service, promotion of positive relationships between Japan and the United States, and his academic career and endeavors relating to academia comprise elements of his public activities. However, the line of demarcation between the two spheres of activity blurs often, and documents like correspondence frequently contain information related to a myriad of topics, such as his family life, academic activities, and participation in Sister Cities International programs. Likewise, many series contain inter-related and complementary materials.
The PERSONAL FILES includes documents relating to Burks' family, his education from high school through graduate studies, and his career as a professional academic. Subjects within the PUBLIC RELATIONS FILES derive from Burks' military career, his status as a member of the faculty and administration of Rutgers University, his authoritative opinions regarding Japan and U.S.-Japanese relations, and his participation in international affairs. However, articles about or informed by Burks can be found throughout the collection, particularly in the CORRESPONDENCE AND DOCUMENTS series.
CORRESPONDENCE AND DOCUMENTS covers the greatest breadth of topics. All facets of Burks' life are found in this series; material ranges from Burks' letters to his wife to his participation in the Jane Voorhees Zimmerli Art Museum's programs. The bulk of the series consists of correspondence between Burks and others in his professional capacities as a writer, administrator, teacher, and active researcher. The promotion of ties between Japan and the United States in a myriad of forms generated a substantial portion of the documents.
In contrast, the MILITARY SERVICE FILES is a narrowly defined series concerning Burks' training and service as a naval language and intelligence officer. The TRAVEL FILES series is also a relatively discrete series relating to Burks' travel throughout the world. The majority of his peregrinations relate, albeit sometimes indirectly, to his academic work in the form of research trips and conference travel; the Yatoi conference in Japan is particularly prominent. However, this series also includes documentation of purely personal excursions, such as the trip to Belize in 1993.
The SUBJECT FILES series primarily consists of material documenting participation in formal academic institutions such as professional organizations and research centers. This material complements and intertwines with material generated by Burks' international activities and promotion of relationships between individuals and institutions within the United States and Japan.
The LECTURES AND PAPERS, COLLECTED PUBLICATIONS, AND UNIVERSITY SEMINAR ON MODERN EAST ASIA: JAPAN series all contain inter-related material generated by Burks' academic career. The LECTURES AND PAPERS contains the broadest range of material, including Burks' published and unpublished writings, his teaching materials, documents accrued by Burks, and material generated by his participation in innovative academic institutions. The SEMINAR ON MODERN EAST ASIA: JAPAN series directly relates to one such institution, Columbia's Seminar on Modern East Asia: Japan, and contains copies of papers circulated for the seminar from its commencement. The COLLECTED PUBLICATIONS series is also discrete, comprised solely of publications, in contrast to the unpublished papers collected by Burks in the LECTURES AND PAPERS series.
The only non-paper format materials in the collection is the PHOTOGRAPHS series. This includes slides, prints, negatives and a scrapbook. Portraiture of Burks and his family, prints documenting official events, and reproductions of Griffis-related research material constitute this series.
Burks himself has annotated several documents within the collection.
Material concerning and generated by Jane Lyle Burks is interspersed throughout the collection.
Oversize materials have been stored separately.
Newspaper clippings throughout this collection have been photocopied for preservation and the originals discarded. However, full size newspaper pages are located in the oversize folders.
Related Collections Note:
Material about Burks can also be found in the Griffis-Related sub-group of the William Elliot Griffis Collection (MC 1015) in Special Collections and University Archives, Rutgers University Libraries.
Arrangement of Collection
I. Personal Files, 1928-1993
II. Public Relations Files, 1939-1995
III. Military Service Files, 1939-1954
IV. Correspodence and Document Files, 1930-1996
V. Travel Files, 1951-1993
VI. Subject Files, 1949-1994
VII. Lectures and Papers, 1938-1995
VIII. Collected Publications, 1951-1992
IX. Columbia University Seminar on Modern East Asia: Japan, 1961-1995
X. Photographs, 1940-c.1993
Detailed Description of the Collection
- I. PERSONAL FILES, 1928-1993, (.5 cubic feet)
  Arrangement: by subject and thereunder chronologically.
  Summary: divided into academic-related and family-related material; thereunder arranged chronologically.
  Material relating to Dr. Burks' family, education, and professional activities. The bulk of this series concerns Dr. Burks' academic career, both as a student, from high school through graduate education, and as a professional academic at Rutgers University. Documents concerning his family include genealogical information; estate information for his brother, father, and mother-in law; and papers concerning his relationship with his wife, Jane Lyle Burks, until her death. Document types vary, including newspaper clippings, event programs, curricula vitae, transcripts, correspondence, cards, and legal documents.
  Of interest is material generated around the outbreak of World War II, including newspaper clippings, speeches Burks gave on peace during his time at the University of Cincinnati and the University of Minnesota (1936-1942), and Burks' work at the International Relations Bureau while at the University of Minnesota. This series also includes oversized material
  - Transcripts, 1939-1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Norwood High School, 1932 and 1982 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - University of Cincinnati, 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
  - University of Cincinnati, Tau Kappa Alpha, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - University of Minnesota, 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Curricula Vitae, 1941-1994 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Rutgers Personnel Data, 1947-1981 (Box 1, Folder 11-13)
  - Retirement, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Genealogy, 1932-1944 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Jane Lyle's Education, 1928 and 1941 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Burks-Lyle Marriage, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Family Documents, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Riki Burks' Adoption, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Estate Papers, 1956-1978 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Jane Burks' Autobiography and Accompanying Material, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Jane Burks, 1989-1993 (Box 2, Folder 8-13)
- II. PUBLIC RELATIONS FILES, 1939-1995, (2 folders)
  Arrangement: chronological.
  Summary: arranged chronologically.
  Articles and press releases either about or citing Burks. Topics include his military service, lecture tours, renewal of ties with Japan, and reviews of his works.
  Of particular interest are articles pertaining to his role in the Doolittle raids on Tokyo during World War II, and articles about the Japanese government awarding him the Order of the Rising Sun, Gold Rays with Neck Ribbon (1990).
  Includes oversize material.
  - 1939-1995 (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
- III. MILITARY SERVICE FILES, 1939-1954, (.4 cubic feet)
  Summary: Arranged chronologically.
  Material pertaining to Burks' military service. The bulk of the documents relates to his intelligence work while in the Naval Reserves. This series contains maps, telegraphs, correspondence, military documents, publications, class notes, personal notes, and intelligence reports.
  Information on Jane Burks' service is incorporated into this series.
  - Confidential, 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - 1939-1942 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  - Desk-top Calendar Jottings, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
  - 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 6-9)
  - Miscellaneous, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 1946-1949 (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
  - 1950-1954 and Undated (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
- IV. CORRESPONDENCE AND DOCUMENT FILES, 1930-1996, (4 cubic feet)
  Arrangement: chronologically and alphabetically.
  Summary: general material is arranged chronologically; topically organized material is arranged alphabetically.
  Correspondence of Burks and supporting documents. This series also contains memoranda, newspaper clippings, newsletters, personal cards, and event programs.
  Burks maintained epistolary contact with a wide variety of individuals, including academic colleagues in the United States and Japan, former students, administrators at Rutgers University and other institutions, diplomatic personnel, and personal friends.
  Of particular interest throughout this series is information on the formation of sister ties between New Jersey and the Fukui Prefecture, New Brunswick and the city of Fukui, and Rutgers University and the Fukui University. Other noteworthy material pertains to Burks' efforts to create the Department of Asian Studies at Rutgers University, which culminated in his appointment as the first professor of Asian Studies effective July 1, 1977, and the commencement of the Institutes on Asian Cultures at Rutgers University in 1961. Starting in 1992, Burks became active in the Jane Voorhees Zimmerli Art Museum, including sitting on the Board of Directors for the Friends of the Zimmerli Art Museum.
  Interspersed throughout this series is material by or about Jane Burks and her activities.
  - General, 1930-1953 (Box 4, Folder 3-16)
  - General, 1953-1995 (Box 5-14)
  - General, 1995-1996 and Undated (Box 15, Folder 1-5)
  - Arbor Glen of Bridgewater, 1989-1994 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Bonn, George - Correspondence, 1985-1991 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Book Notes, circa 1954 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Kaneko, Tadashi - Correspondence, 1969-1977 (Box 15, Folder 9-10)
  - Matsumura, Mayoshi; Japan Foundation - Correspondence, 1986-1989 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Miki, Yukiharu - Memorial Papers, 1965 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Shibata, Tokue - Correspondence, 1966-1978 (Box 15, Folder 13-14)
  - Tanabe, Tatsuro; International House, Tokyo - Correspondence, 1969-1974 and 1983-1988 (Box 15, Folder 15-16)
  - Yim, Yong Soon - Correspondence, 1971-1975 (Box 15, Folder 17)
- V. TRAVEL FILES, 1951-1993, (1 cubic feet)
  Material pertaining to Burks' travel to Europe, Asia, and South America. The majority of his trips were for professional reasons: to participate in conferences, to engage in research, or to represent Rutgers or New Brunswick in Fukui. Document types include correspondence, memoranda, itineraries, brochures, and programs.
  This series contains material generated by the Second International Symposium on Yatoi (1985), for which Burks served as an honorary chairman, including unpublished and published conference papers.
  - Japan, 1951-1952 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Hong Kong, 1953 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Japan, 1958-1959 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Japan, 1965 (Box 16, Folder 4-6)
  - Bermuda, 1968 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Japan, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 8-9)
  - Japan, 1973 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Japan, 1978 (Box 16, Folder 11-13)
  - Japan and China, 1970 (Box 17, Folder 1-3)
  - Mexico, 1980 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Japan, 1982 (Box 17, Folder 5-6)
  - Mediterranean, 1982 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - USSR, 1984 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Japan, pre-Yatoi Conference, 1985 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Japan, Yatoi Conference, 1985 (Box 17, Folder 10-11)
  - Japan, post- Yatoi Conference, 1985-1988 (Box 18, Folder 1-2)
  - Aspen, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Alaska, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Japan, 1988 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Helsinki, Stockholm, Leningrad, 1989 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Unknown, 1990 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Japan, 1992-1993 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Japan, 1978 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Travel Retrospective, 1994 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Anguilla, 1995 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Japan, Undated (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - China, Undated (Box 18, Folder 13)
- VI. SUBJECT FILES, 1949-1994, (2.3 cubic feet)
  Summary: arranged alphabetically by subject and thereunder chronologically.
  This series contains material concerning Burks' involvement in organizations and academic endeavors. Said activities included promoting the ties between New Jersey and Japan through the Sister State, City, and University programs and attendant activities; organizing conferences both within and external to Rutgers University; and active membership in organizations such as the American Association of University Professors (AAUP), the Association for Asian Studies (AAS), and the New Jersey Association of Colleges and Universities (NJACU). The bulk of the documents are correspondence. Additional document types include newspaper articles, press releases, meeting minutes, newsletters, memoranda, grant searches, and event programs.
  Material of interest includes documents on the dismissal of Rutgers' professors Heimlich, Finley, and Glasser during the McCarthy era, and on the New Jersey loyalty oaths in the 1950s (found in the AAUP files).
  - American Association of University Professors, 1949-1960 (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - Association for Asian Studies (AAS); Northeast Asia Regional Council of the AAS (NEARC); Mid-Atlantic Region AAS (MAR), 1972-1990 (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - Japan, 1958-1959 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - AAS; NEARC; MAR, 1972-1990 (Box 19, Folder 1-2)
  - Cincinnati Council on World Affairs, 1966-1973 (Box 19, Folder 3-4)
  - Consultation on International Exchange, 1967 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Council on International Educational Exchange, 1970-1974 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Fukui, 1965-1985 (Box 19, Folder 7-12)
  - Fukui, 1995 (Box 19, Folder 13-14)
  - Fulbright-Hiags Programs, 1966 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Hemlich, Finley, and Glasser Cases, 1953-1958 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - International Center for Japonisme Conference, 1988-1989 (Box 20, Folder 3-5)
  - International Center for Japonisme, 1991-1994 (Box 20, Folder 6-7)
  - International Education, 1965 (Box 21, Folder 1-2)
  - International Education, 1967-1977 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - International Education, 1972 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - International Education, 1981 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Jane Burks' Speech on Child Welfare, 1952 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Jane Burks' Notes and Translations on Childcare in Japan, 1952-1953 (Box 21, Folder 7-9)
  - Jane Burks' Paper on Families, Undated (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Japanese Bankers Program, 1974 (Box 21, Folder 11-13)
  - Japan Foundation, 1973-1980 (Box 22, Folder 1-2)
  - Japan Scholarship Foundation, 1950-1966 (Box 22, Folder 3-6)
  - New Jersey Association of Colleges and Universities (NJACU), Memos and Policies, 1974-1978 (Box 22, Folder 7-8)
  - NJACU, Books, Commission General, 1976-1978 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - NJACU Meeting Minutes, 1976-1979 (Box 22, Folder 10-11)
  - NJACU Newsletters, 1977-1978 (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - Ohara School of Flower Arrangement, Undated (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - Report on College of Arts and Sciences Self-Study, 1953 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Robins-Mowry Manuscript, The Hidden Sun, 1981 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Sister Cities, 1977 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Sister Cities, 1985-1993 (Box 23, Folder 4-11)
  - Sister Cities, 1994 and Undated (Box 24, Folder 1-2)
  - Sister Cities, Hungary, 1992 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Tokyo Metropolitan Institute of Municipal Research, 1965-1966 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Toyota Foundation, 1978 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - United Nations Conference, 1972 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - University of Hawaii, 1976-1984 (Box 24, Folder 7-8)